Giulio V. Blanc
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Giulio V. Blanc papers
1920-1995
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Giulio V. Blanc
11 linear feet
The dates for the Giulio V. Blanc papers range from 1920-1995. Measuring a total of eleven linear feet, the collection provides documentation of the art exhibitions Blanc curated during his career, including original writings and exhibition catalogs. The extensive artists files in the collection provide information on numerous Latin American and Caribbean artists. The collection also provides historical information on the life and culture of Cuba.
Biographical Note
Independent curator, critic, art historian and consultant Giulio V. Blanc (1955-1995) specialized in Cuban and Latin American art history and in his lifetime collected a wealth of material on the subject. Through his numerous exhibitions and keen articles appearing in national and international art journals, Blanc became a leading authority on Latin American art and successfully established himself as a link between Cuban and Cuban-American artists and US galleries and museums. The Miami Generation (1983) and Amelia Peláez: A Retrospective (1988) are two significant exhibitions Blanc curated for Miami's Cuban Museum of Arts and Culture in addition to the celebrated Wifredo Lam and His Contemporaries, 1938-1952 (1992) for New York's Studio Museum in Harlem. Giulio V. Blanc was among the key figures that catapulted Latin American art onto the mainstream in the early 1980s.
Giulio V. Blanc was born in Havana in 1955 to Baron Lodovico Blanc and María V. Blanc. The Blanc name hails from Italy and the title of Baron was awarded to Alberto Blanc, Lodovico Blanc's grandfather, while he was Secretary of State in 1873 under Victor Emmanuel II of Italy. As young advocates of Cuban culture, the Blanc's collected a number of paintings by Cuban artists but were forced to leave behind the works of Cuban masters such as Carlos Enríquez, Victor Manuel, René Portocarrero, Fidelio Ponce and others to facilitate an uncomplicated exodus from the country during the revolution. Lodovico and María were in their thirties and Giulio was five years old when the family settled in Miami.
Giulio Blanc completed his undergraduate education at Harvard and proceeded to Brown University and the Institute of Fine Arts in New York for graduate work (1979-1980). During his career, he served as an independent curator and consultant to The Cuban Museum of Arts and Culture (Miami), The Metropolitan Museum (Miami), and The Museum of Contemporary Hispanic Art (New York) among others. He also lectured on Latin American art history at the Art Museum of the Americas, OAS (Organization of American States), Washington, DC, The University of Miami, and El Museo Nacional de Arte in La Paz, Bolivia. In addition, he worked as a consultant in the Latin American Paintings Department at Sotheby's auction house in New York and served on the editorial board of the magazine Art Nexus. Blanc was pursuing a doctoral degree in art history at the City University of New York before his premature death in 1995 at the age of thirty-nine.
Date Event
1955 Born November 1 in Havana, Cuba to Baron Lodovico and Baroness María V. Blanc, young collectors of Cuban art. The title of Baron was awarded to Alberto Blanc, Lodovico Blanc's grandfather, in 1873 while Alberto was Secretary of State under Victor Emmanuel II of Italy.
1960 The Blanc family migrates to the United States because of the escalating revolution. Lodovico and Maria V. Blanc are in their thirties when they flee the island. The works of Cuban painters such as Carlos Enríquez, Victor Manuel, René Portocarrero, Fidelio Ponce and others were left behind to facilitate an uncomplicated exodus.
1976 Giulio V. Blanc serves as research assistant for one year at the Tozzer Library, Peabody Museum, Harvard University.
1977 Graduates cum laude from Harvard College with a B.A. in Archeology.
1979 Graduates from Brown University with a M.A. in Archeology. Was a research assistant until 1980 at the Gallery of the Center for Inter-American Relations, New York city.
1980 Receives a certificate in Museum Studies from the Graduate School of Arts and Science, New York University. Curates Emilio Sánchez: Lithographs which opens at the Pagoda, Ransom-Everglades School, Coconut Grove, Florida. Co-curates Cuba in the Nineteenth Century for Miami's Miami-Dade Public Library.
1981 Joins the Latin American Paintings Department, Sotheby's Auction House, New York and serves for two years.
1982 Co-curates Young Hispanics, USA which opens at the Lehigh University Museum, Bethlehem, Pennsylvania and curates Ten Out of Cuba for INTAR Latin American Gallery in New York.
1983 Curates Cuban Fantasies at the Kouros Gallery in New York and Pablo Cano en Paris for the 4 Place de Saussaies in Paris, France. Also curates The Miami Generation: Nine Cuban-American Artists for the Cuban Museum of Arts and Culture in Miami and the Meridian House in Washington, DC.
1984 Serves as independent curator and consultant to Miami's Metropolitan Museum and Art Center and The Cuban Museum of Arts and Culture; The Museum of Contemporary Hispanic Art in New York and other institutions. Lectures at the Art Museum of the Americas (Organization of American States) in Washington, DC; The University of Miami; The Cuban Museum of Arts and Culture (Miami); The Center for the Fine Arts (Miami); Rockland Center for the Arts (West Nyack, NY); and the National Museum of Art, La Paz, Bolivia. Curates Young Collector's of Latin American Art which opened at Miami's Metropolitan Museum and Art Center.
1985 Curates Dancing Faces: An Exhibition of Mexican Masks for the Metropolitan Museum and Art Center in Miami and Nuevas Vistas: Latin American Paintings which opens at the Wistariahurst, Holyoke, Massachusetts. Curates Architecture in Cuban Painting, for the Miami Dade Public Library.
1986 Receives and M.A. in Art History at New York University's Institute of Fine Arts. Curates Carlos Enríquez for the Cuban Museum of Arts and Culture, Miami, Florida and Into the Mainstream: Ten Latin American Artists Working in New York for the Jersey City Museum in Jersey City, New Jersey.
1987 The exhibition Aurelia Muñoz: Selections, curated by Blanc, opens at the Metropolitan Museum of Art in Miami, Florida. Serves as juror for Expresiones Hispanas: Coors National Hispanic Art Exhibition, Denver, Colorado. Curates Visions of Self: The American Latin Artist for the Miami-Dade Community College gallery.
1988 Receives a grant from the NY State Council on the Arts for research on Cuban artist Wifredo Lam for the exhibition at the Studio Museum in Harlem, New York. Enrolls in the art history Ph.D. program at the City University Graduate Center, New York city. First bombing of the Cuban Museum of Arts and Culture in Miami takes place. Blanc's Amelia Peláez: A Retrospective successfully opens at the Cuban Museum of Arts and Culture despite much controversy.
1989 Curates Urgent Dream: New Work by Mario Bencomo at the Museum of Contemporary Hispanic Art (MoCHA), New York. Second bombing of the Cuban Museum of Arts and Culture, Miami FL.
1990 New York correspondent for Arte en Colombia, Bogota. Serves as adjunct lecturer at Queens College (CUNY) for the Fall semester. Curates the exhibition, The Post-Miami Generation for the Inter-American Gallery in Miami, Florida. Co-curates Figurative Perspectives: Six Artists of Latin American Background for the Rockland Center for the Arts, West Nyack, NY.
1991 Visiting scholar at University of Massachusetts at Amherst. Writes a small play, Tía Carmela: A Cuban Tragicomedy, illustrated by Cuban artist and friend Pablo Cano.
1995 Dies at the age of forty of AIDS related complications.
Scope and Content Note
The Giulio V. Blanc papers measure approximately 11 linear feet and date from 1920 to 1995. Compiled by Blanc since the beginning of his curatorial, writing, and research career in the 1980s, the papers consist primarily of artist files on Cuban, Cuban-American, and Latin American artists (1920-1995 and undated). Also found is biographical information (1994-1995), interviews by Blanc (1984-1987, 1994) and miscellaneous letters from artists and friends (1983-1995 and undated).
The first series, Biographical Files, 1994-1995 includes information about Blanc's career. Series 2: Miscellaneous Letters, 1983-1995, undated, consists of letters from artists and friends on various topics. Series 3: Artist Files, 1920-1995, undated, represents the bulk of the collection (approximately 300 artists in all, 6 linear feet), and contain materials either collected by Blanc or received by Blanc from the artists themselves. These consist of biographical material about the artist, usually two or three paragraphs written by Blanc, scattered resumes and copies of fellowship applications. Also found are newspaper clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, and letters or correspondence between Blanc and the artists. Of special interest in this series are numerous taped interviews with celebrated Cuban artists and art historians such as José Gómez Sícre, founder and first director of the Art Museum of the Americas, Organization of American States. Gómez-Sícre describes his early career and involvement with acquisitions for the museum's permanent collection as well as his working relationship with Alfred H. Barr, first director of the Museum of Modern Art in New York. Gómez-Sícre's notable book, Pintura Cubana de Hoy, published in Havana in 1944 is included in the files.
Elena Peláez de Medero, another interviewee, discusses her sister, Cuban painter Amelia Peláez (1896-1968). Blanc interviewed Elena Peláez in Miami for his 1988 exhibition Amelia Peláez: A Retrospective. The Peláez file includes Blanc's correspondence with her as well as copies of rare 1930s and 1940s exhibition catalogs from Amelia Peláez's early career. Among the catalogs is a copy of Modern Cuban Painters from the 1944 exhibition held at the Museum of Modern Art in New York. Also found are rare French, German and Spanish newspaper clippings on Peláez dating back to the 1920s. Of interest is a copy of Amado Blanco's 1937 poetry book, Poema desesperado. Published in Havana, the book is dedicated to the memory of Federico García Lorca and includes illustrations by Peláez.
Another prominent artist whom Blanc interviewed was Enrique Riverón (b. 1901) leader of the Cuban vanguardia. He was a member of El Grupo de Montparnasse, a talented group of painters and writers living in the southern district of Paris in the late 1920s, an area noted for its boisterous after-hour activities. The interview was published in the Journal of Decorative and Propaganda Arts in 1997. Also found in the papers are illustrated letters and greeting cards addressed to Blanc and his parents, Baron Lodovico Blanc and María V. Blanc.
Series 4: Exhibition Files, 1977-1995, undated, consists primarily of material Blanc compiled for exhibitions he curated. Found here are letters from museum directors, artists and colleagues, drafts and finished essays for exhibition catalogs, and printed material such as newspaper clippings of art reviews. This series also includes files on exhibitions Blanc did not curate.
Series 5: Subject Files, 1933-1995, undated, are files relating to Cuban art, culture, and society, the Cuban revolution, book projects, Biennials in Havana and São Paulo, the 1988 controversy surrounding the Cuban Museum of Arts and Culture (Miami, FL) and other topics. Found are letters, drafts of writings, notes, printed material such as newspaper clippings and magazine articles, press releases, and exhibition announcements.
Particularly extensive is the documentation about the 1980s conflict at the Cuban Museum of Arts and Culture. In April 1988, a fund-raising auction at the 24-year-old `little Havana' institution resulted in heated disputes that escalated to violence. The works auctioned were by Cuban artists still living on the island. Many in Miami's Cuban community considered these artists to be supporters of the Communist regime and were outraged. One of the disputed works purchased the night of the auction, a drawing by Manuel Mendive, was taken across the street by its successful bidder and burned. In addition, the museum building was damaged by a pipe bomb shortly after the sale. In the National Public Radio news story (available in Blanc's papers on audio cassette) Helen Kohen, critic for the Miami Herald commented, “We're not talking about paintings. We're talking about `my brother's in jail'. That's what we're talking about.” The situation intensified quickly; transcending local politics and involving the Treasury and Justice Departments, the American Civil Liberties Union, the Federal Bureau of Investigation, and Sotheby's and Christie's auction houses. Ramón Cernuda, the museum vice-president who organized the auction also had his personal collection of Cuban art impounded by the FBI. A second bombing took place in 1989 to protest an exhibition of Cuban artists who came to the U. S. during the early 1980s Mariel boatlift.
The seriousness of the conflicts in the Miami museum prompted the Museum of Modern Art in New York to withdraw an offer to lend three paintings to the Cuban museum for the 1988 exhibition Amelia Peláez: A Retrospective scheduled to open later that year. Curated by Giulio Blanc, it was the first U.S. retrospective of this important Cuban artist and the exhibition helped situate her work. The Cuban Museum of Art in Daytona Beach, an institution that helped start the Miami museum, also withdrew an offer to lend “Amelias”. The result was an exhibition devoid of works owned by the Museum of Modern Art, important paintings created after 1963, the year President Kennedy imposed economic sanctions on Cuba.
To publicize the Peláez exhibition and boost attendance, the museum placed a public invitation in the Spanish section of the Miami Herald. The half page ad, also found in the Blanc papers, lists more than 100 intellectuals and professionals who supported the exhibition. Blanc stated in a letter to the Miami Herald, “ It is horrifying to think there are those in Miami who would burn a painting for the sake of politics. This was the same reasoning utilized by Joseph Goebbels when he made bonfires of books and paintings by anti-Nazi and `degenerate' artists and writers in 1930s Germany... One can only pity the ignorance of those who play into the hands of the Castro regime by resorting to uncivilized tactics that can only hurt the image of the Cuban-exile community and of Miami in general.”
The files concerning the Cuban Museum of Arts and Culture contain exhibition announcements, copies of court orders, press releases and correspondence between Blanc and the Museum of Modern Art in New York regarding the museum and the Peláez exhibition. Also included are a great number of newspaper articles printed in two of Miami's major newspapers, the Miami Herald and El Nuevo Herald which covered the story until it was resolved in the early 1990s. Offering additional information on the controversy are a number of letters addressed to either Blanc or his parents from artists and friends expressing either discontent with the museum's state of affairs or gratitude for the Blanc's financial support during the museum's reconstruction. These provide remarkable insight into a relatively heterogeneous Cuban community.
Series 6: Sound Recordings, 1992, 1994 consists of two untranscribed audio cassette tapes. One is of the 1992 College Art Association's session: Artistic Voices of Latin America: The Aesthetics of Anti-Colonialism held in Chicago, Illinois in which Giulio V. Blanc was a panelist. The other is a rare 1994 interview conducted by Blanc with poet-priest Monseñor Angel Gaztelu, a friend of many Cuban writers and artists, and who presided over Peláez's funeral service in 1968.
The last series, Series 7: Photographs, 1981-1993, undated, includes black and whiteportraits of artists, group shots of Blanc with “Miami Generation” artists María Brito, Pablo Cano, María Martínez-Cañas, Carlos Macía, Arturo Rodríguez, and César Trasobares, and photos of other artists.
Arrangement
The Giulio V. Blanc papers are arranged into seven series primarily according to type of material. Within each series, materials are arranged chronologically, except for Artist Files and Subject Files which are arranged alphabetically by either name or subject.
Series 1: Biographical Files, 1994-1995, undated (box 1; 3 folders)
Series 2: Miscellaneous Letters, 1983-1995, undated (box 1; 3 folders)
Series 3: Artist Files, 1920-1995, undated(boxes 1-8; 6 linear ft.)
Series 4: Exhibition Files, 1977-1995, undated (box 8; 1 linear foot)
Series 5: Subject Files, 1933-1995, undated (boxes 8-12; 2.5 linear feet)
Series 6: Untranscribed Sound Recordings, 1992-1994 (box 12; 2 folders)
Series 7: Photographs, 1981, 1993, undated (box 12; 2 folders)
Appendix: Printed Material from Artists Files for Wifredo Lam, Amelia Peláez, and Enrique Riverón
Wifredo Lam: Exhibition and Auction Announcements and Invitations, 1955-1996
1955: Wifredo Lam, Pabellón de Ciencias Sociales, Havana
1969: Wifredo Lam on Paper, Cisneros Gallery, New York
1982: Homenaje a Wifredo Lam, Museo Español de Arte Comtemporáneo, Madrid
1984: Important Latin American Paintings, Drawings, and Sculpture, Sotheby's, New York
1987: Wifredo Lam, Galerie Albert Loeb, Paris
1987: Wifredo Lam: Peintures, Galerie Maeght Lelong, Paris
1992: Rumbas &f Love Songs: The Musical Canvas of Wifredo Lam, Symphony Space, New York
1992: Wifredo Lam, Museo Nacional Centro de Arte Reina Sofía, Madrid
1993: Wifredo Lam: The Annonciation di Aimé Cesaire, Fedric Snitzer Gallery, Coral Gables
1994: Wifredo Lam: Oeuvre Gravé et Lithographié, Musee du Dessin et de L'Estampe Originale de Gravelines, Paris
1996: Wifredo Lam: Catalogue Raissone, Gary Nader Gallery, Coral Gables
Wilfredo Lam: Exhibition brochures and catalogs, 1950-1993
1950: Exposicíon Lam: Obras Recientes, Havana
1955: Exposicíon Lam, Museo de Bellas Artes, Caracas
1959: Lam, Galleria Pagani, Milan
1969: Wifredo Lam: Exposicion de Pinturas, Casa de Cultura, Cuenca
1971: Wilfredo Lam, Gimpel Gallery, New York
1977: Wilfredo Lam, Galeria Meindl, Bogota
1978: Lam, Gissi Galleria d'Arte, Torino
1980: Wifredo Lam, Galleri D'Arte La Borgognona, Rome
1981: Max Ernst-Wifredo Lam: Paintings, Watercolors and Graphics, Guild Gallery, New York
1992: Afro-Caribbean Culture: The World of Wifredo Lam, The Americas Society, The Studio Museum in Harlem and the Symphony Space, New York
1993: Wifredo Lam: Museo Nacional Palacio de Bellas Artes, Havana
Undated: Winter Calendar, The Studio Museum in Harlem, New York
Amelia Peláez: Exhibition Announcements, Invitations and Brochures, 1988, undated
1977: Amelia Peláez, Metropolitan Museum and Art Centers, Miami
1988: Amelia Peláez 1896-1968: A Retrospective, Museum of Modern Art of Latin America, Washington DC
1988: Amelia Peláez 1896-1968: A Retrospective/Una RetrosPerspe, Cubann Museum of Arts and Culture, Miami
1988: Fall calendar, Museum of Modern Art, Organization of American States, Washington DC
Undated: Information on artist, Organization of American States, Washington, DC
Amelia Peláez: Exhibition Catalogs, 1930s-1980s, 1991
1933: Exposition: Amelia Pelaez del Casal, Galérie Zak, Paris
1935: Exposición: Amelia Pelaez del Casal, Lyceum, Havana
1937: Dance International 1900-1937: Exhibit of Arts Relating to the Dance, Rockefeller Center, New York
1941: Peláez, Norte Gallery, New York
1943: Amelia Peláez: Retrospective 1929-1943, Institución Hispano-Cubana de Cultura, Havana
1968: Amelia Peláez: Exposición Retrospectiva, Museo Nacional Palacio de Bellas Artes, Havana (2 copies)
1977: Amelia Peláez, Metropolitan Museum and Art Centers, Miami
1977: Cuba Peintres D'aujourd'hui, Musée d'Art Moderne de la Ville de Paris, Paris [Incomplete]
1979: La Gran Pintora Cubana Amelia Peláez, Museo de Arte Moderno, Mexico City
1980: Amelia Peláez: Oleos Tempera y Tinta, Museo de Arte Moderno, Bogota
1986: Amelia Peláez: Exposición Antologica, Pinturas 1929-1967, Museo Nacional de Bellas Artes, Havana
1991: Amelia Peláez: Exposición Retrospectiva, 1924-1967, Museo Nacional de Bellas Artes, Caracas
Enrique Riverón: Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1957-1994, undated
1926: Enrique Riverón, Association Paris Amerique Latine, Paris
1957: Riverón, Sudamericana Gallery, New York
1958: Retrospective Exhibition: Riverón, Wichita Art Museum, Wichita
1960: Enrique Riverón, Arger Gallery, Coral Gables
1961: Riverón, Gallery of Modern Arts, Sante Fe
1965: Riverón, Bacardi Art Gallery, Miami
1965: Riverón, Museum of Modern Art, Miami
1969: Enter the Sun: New Paintings by Riverón, Pageant Gallery, Miami
1973: Gala: Grupo de Artistas Latinoamericanos, Bacardi Art Gallery, Miami
1974: Riverón Retrospective Exhibition, Bacardi Art Gallery, Miami
1977: Bermudez, Davila, Fernández, Riverón, Velazquez, Forma Gallery, Coral Gables
1980:Riverón: 1925-1950 Paris/La Habana /New York, Lowe Art Museum, Coral Gables
1980: Riverón: 1950-1980 Wichita/Coconut Grove, De Armas Gallery, Virginia Gardens
1983: Riverón, Gallery at Grove Isle, Coconut Grove
1987: Enrique Riverón: Recent Works, Bacardi Art Gallery, Miami
1994: Alfonzo, Espada, Iraola, Marin, Riverón, Barbara Greene's, Miami
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following index terms. People, families and organizations are listed under "Names" when they are creators or contributors and under "Subjects" when they are the topic of collection contents.
Subjects:
Brito, Maria, 1947-; Cano, Margarita, 1932-; Cano, Pablo; Carreño, Mario; Carulla, Ramón, 1938-; Demi, 1955-; Garcia, Hernan, 1935-; Gattorno, Antonio; Gaztelu, A. (Angel); Goldman, Shifra M., 1926-; Gómez-Peña, Guillermo; Lam, Wifredo; Larraz, Julio; Libin, Victoria; Macia, Carlos A., 1951-1994; Martínez-Cañas, María; Riverón, Enrique; Rodríguez, Arturo, 1956-; Sánchez, Juan, 1954-; Sí, Juan; Trasobares, César; Vater, Regina; Vázquez Lucio, Oscar E. (Oscar Edgardo), 1932-; Cuban Museum of Arts and Culture (Miami, Fla.)
Subjects-Topical:
Artists -- Cuba; Cuban American artists; Cuban American art -- Florida -- Miami; Art, Latin American; Art historians -- Florida -- Miami
Types of Materials:
Sound recordings
Names:
Gaztelu, A. (Angel) interviewee; Cabrera, Lydia interviewee; Gómez Sicre, José interviewee; Riverón, Enrique
Provenance
Margherite Blanc, sister of Giulio V. Blanc, donated her brother's papers in 1998 to the Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution. This collection, along with numerous other Latino collections, was acquired through the 1996 Latino Art Documentation Project in South Florida. Initiated to chronicle the thriving art scene so apparent in the city's galleries, museums, and private collections, the project resulted in numerous acquisitions described in the revised edition of the Papers of Latino and Latin American Artists. Both the project and the publication were made possible, in part, with funding provided by the Smithsonian Institution's Center for Latino Initiatives.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment and is limited to the Washington, D.C. research facility.
Alternative Forms Available
The collection is available on Microfilm Reels # 5476-5487 and for interlibrary loan.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Files, 1994-1995, undated, Series 1:; (box 1; 3 folders)